Guide to the R. Keith Dennis Mathematician Print and Photo collection, circa 1850-1950.
Dennis, R. Keith Mathematician Print and Photo collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
R. Keith Dennis Mathematician Print and Photo collection, circa 1850-1950.
8565
Dennis, R. Keith.
.6
Photographs, Printed materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection consists namely of prints, portraits and photographs of mathematicians.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
R. Keith Dennis is a Professor of Mathematics at Cornell University with a focus area on commutative and non-commutative algebra, algebraic K-theory, group theory, and mathematical bibliography.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists namely of prints, portraits and photographs of mathematicians colelcted by Dennis. Notable historic figures in mathematics are represented. Several published portfolios, including editions of David Eugene Smith's Portraits of Eminent Mathematicians, containing prints and biographical information on the mathematicians are also included. Plates appear to often come from published works and in some cases include portions of text from the book from which they were removed.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Dennis, R. Keith.; Smith, David Eugene, 1860-1944.; Scripta mathematica
Subjects:
Mathematicians; Mathematics -- Study and teaching.
Form and Genre Terms:
Engravings (prints); Photographs
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Oversize items
  Includes:
  Carl Friedrich Gauss
  Karl Weierstrass
  - Panoramic photograph of 1946 mathematical convention, August 1946
    Photograph by Fenner showing the attendees of the 1946 annual meetings of the American Mathematical Society, Institute of Mathematical Statistics, and Mathematical Association of America at Cornell University, photographed in front of Barton Hall.
- Individuals A-C (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Raymond Archibald
  Aristotle
  Isaac Barrow
  Wilhelm Blaschke
  Tycho Brahe
  David Brewster
  William Byerly
  Gerolamo Cardano
  Rudolf Clausius
  Nicolaus Copernicus
  Georges Cuvier
- Individuals D-F (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Jean le Rond d'Alembert
  H. Ted Davis
  Ernest de Jonquières
  René Descartes
  Ron DiPerna
  Martin Eichler
  Epicurus
  Leonhard Euler
  Victor Felber
  Augustin Fresnel
- Individuals G-I (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Galileo Galilei
  Évariste Galois
  Carl Freidrich Gauss
  Sophie Germain
  James Joseph Glaisher
  Edmond Halley
  William Hamilton
  Oliver Heaviside
  Heinrich Hertz
  David Hilbert
  Shirley Hill
  Christiaan Huygens
- Individuals J-L (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Fritz John
  Robert Kalaba
  Immanuel Kant
  Vladimir Karapetoff
  Johannes Kepler
  Cassius Keyser
  Felix Klein
  Joseph-Louis Lagrange
  Gabriel Lamé
  Pierre-Simon Laplace
  Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz
  Joseph-Louis Liouville
  Alfred Loewy
  Gino Loria
- Individuals M-O (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Kurt Mahler
  J. C. P. Miller
  Simon Newcomb
  Isaac Newton
  Amalie Noether
- Individuals P-R (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Georges Papy
  Vilfredo Pareto
  Blaise Pascal
  George Peacock
  Charles Peirce
  Michael Pupin
  K. G. Ramanathan
  Herbert Robbins
- Individuals S-V (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Lao Simons
  David Smith
  William Benjamin Smith
  Mary Somerville
  Benedict Spinoza
  Jacob Steiner
  Charles Steinmetz
  Henry Svoboda
  James Joseph Sylvester
  Giuseppe Tallini
  Paul Tannery
  Olga Taussky-Todd
  John Arthur Todd
  Pieter Venema
  Alexander von Humboldt
- Individuals W-Z (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Alfred Whitehead
  Štefan Znám
- Multiple Individuals and Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Presentation of the Senior Wrangler to the Vice Chancellor, Camridge, January 1872.
  Trinty College A Century Ago
  K. H. W. Kruse, Leslie Comrie, J. T. Peters
  Herbert B. Dwight, Maurice Kraitchik, Horace Uhler
- David Hilbert (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Books and Portfolios
  - Das projektive Zeichnen nebst den für das Zeichnen wichtigsten Aufgaben aus der ebenen Geometrie, 1885 (Box 2)
    By Max Kleiber, published by Wilhelm Effenberger
  - A Portfolio of Portraits of Eminent Mathematicians, 1896 (Box 2)
    By David Eugene Smith, published by The Open Court Publishing Company. Incomplete set, missing several pages. Includes: Pythagoras, Pierre de Fermat, Leonardo Bonacci (2 copies), Euclid, Gerolamo Cardano, Gottfried Wilhelm Liebnitz, John Napier, François Viète, Thales of Miletus, Blaise Pascal, Johann Bernoulli (2 copies), Jakob Bernoulli, Guillaume de l'Hôpital, Bonaventura Cavalieri, Gaspard Monge, Niccolo Tartaglia, Isaac Barrow (spelled Issac).
  - Portraits of Eminent Mathematicians Portfolio Number One, 1936 (Box 2)
    By David Eugene Smith, puclished by Scripta Mathematica. Includes: Archimedes, Nicolaus Copernicus, François Viète, Galileo Galilei, John Napier, René Descartes, Isaac Newton (missing), Gottfried Wilhelm Liebnitz, Joseph-Louis Lagrange, Carl Freidrich Gauss (missing), Nikolai Lobachevsky, James Joseph Sylvester.
  - Portraits of Eminent Mathematicians Portfolio Number Two, 1938 (Box 2)
    By David Eugene Smith, puclished by Scripta Mathematica. Includes: Euclid, Gerolamo Cardano, Johannes Kepler, Pierre de Fermat (missing), Blaise Pascal, Leonhard Euler (missing), Pierre-Simon Laplace, Augustin-Louis Cauchy, Carl Gustav Jacob Jacobi, William Rowan Hamilton, Arthur Cayley (missing), Pafnuty Chebyshev, Henri Poincaré (missing).
  - Portraits of Eminent Mathematicians Portfolio Number Two (copy 2), 1938 (Box 2)
    By David Eugene Smith, puclished by Scripta Mathematica. Includes: Euclid (missing), Gerolamo Cardano, Johannes Kepler, Pierre de Fermat (missing), Blaise Pascal, Leonhard Euler (missing), Pierre-Simon Laplace, Augustin-Louis Cauchy, Carl Gustav Jacob Jacobi, William Rowan Hamilton, Arthur Cayley (missing), Pafnuty Chebyshev, Henri Poincaré (missing).
  - Portraits of Famous Philosophers who were also Mathematicians, 1939 (Box 2)
    By Cassius Jackson Keyser, published by Scripta Mathematica
    Includes: Pyhagoras, Plato, Aristotle, Epicurus, Roger Bacon, René Descartes, Blaise Pascal, Benedict Spinoza, Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz, George Berkeley, Immanuel Kant, Charles Peirce
  - Portraits of Famous Physicists, 1942 (Box 2)
    By Henry Crew, published by Scripta Mathematica. Includes: Galileo, Christiaan Huygens, Isaac Nweton, André-Marie Ampère, Augustin Fresnel, Michael Faraday, James Prescott Joule, Rudolf Julius Emmanuel Clausius, James Clerk Maxwell, Josiah Willard Gibbs, Heinrich Rudolf Hertz, Henry Augustus Rowland.